Guide to the Allegheny Observatory Records, 1850-1977 UA.5.1
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Allegheny Observatory Records
1850-1977
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Allegheny Observatory
UA.5.1
43.5 Linear Feet (98 boxes)
The Astronomical Observatory was founded in 1858 by the Allegheny Telescope Association in Allegheny, PA (now the North Side of Pittsburgh) and deeded to the Western University of Pennsylvania (now the University of Pittsburgh) in 1867. The records contain directors files, administrative files, notebooks, drawings, mechanical drawings, photographic prints and negatives, news releases, newsclippings, historical documents, and articles written about the Observatory. Digital reproductions of selected photographs are available online.
History
The appearance of the comet known as "Donati's Comet", discovered in Florence by Giovanni Donati on June 2, 1858, gave the initial stimulus to the founding of the observatory. Interest in the comets appearance caused a group of men (professional and business) to form the Allegheny Telescope Association. This group, among whom the most prominent were Professor Louis Bradley, Josiah King and Harvey Childs, met in Bradley's home on February 15, 1858, and resolved not only to found the A.T.A. but also to purchase a telescope.
On January 31, 1860, the A.T.A. ordered a 13-inch telescope from Henry Fitz of New York, and it was installed in 1861. On May 15, 1860, the A.T.A. officially adopted a constitution and by-laws, elected a board of directors, and appointed an Observatory Committee. This committee raised funds by subscription for the telescope and housed it in a new building which they called the "Allegheny Observatory" as it was centered on a hill on Perrysville Avenue in the old city of Allegheny.
Professor Bradley was custodian of the new telescope from 1861-1863. In 1865, Professor Philotus Dean, principal of Central High School in Pittsburgh, became first custodian of the Observatory. Both men served without pay, accepting the responsibility of the Observatory to promote the advance of science. Later in 1865, the A.T.A. deeded the telescope, the building and the land to the Western University of Pennsylvania (now University of Pittsburgh). In 1867, the official transfer was completed and Samuel Langley was appointed Director. Among many other accomplishments, Langley invented a device to measure the temperatures on the Sun's surface, known as a bolometer; "Standardized" time for railroad companies; and coined the terms "astrophysics" and "aerodynamics"
When Langley left to become Secretary of the Smithsonian in 1887, James Keeler became the acting director and used the 13" Fitz-Clark telescope to discover Saturn's rings were made of small particles instead of being one large disk. In the early 1890s, because of the increasing air pollution in Pittsburgh and the need for larger research facilities, a new building at a new site was designed. The new Allegheny observatory was built between 1900 and 1914 in Riverview Park. The old observatory was sold and at one point a hospital for an orphanage. The building was torn down in 1955.
The Fitz-Clark 13" is still used today. In 1974 a bequest in the memory of George Theiss was made to the Observatory allowing for renovations on the Thaw and Keeler Telescopes. The George W. Theiss Astronomical Laboratory was also established and houses machines used to measure stellar images obtained from telescopes. The Thaw lens was replaced in 1985.
Scope and Content Notes
The records contain correspondence and letterpress books belonging to ten of the observatory's directors, directors' miscellany, notes, articles, and correspondence. Records also include administrative files, notebooks, drawings, mechanical drawings, photographic prints and negatives, news releases, news clippings, a scrapbook, and historical documents and articles written about the Observatory.
Note: Series I (Correspondence of Directors and Acting Directors); Series II (Letterpress books of Directors and Acting Directors); and Series IV (Correspondence of affiliated astronomers) have been microfilmed. A detailed unpublished index to items in those series appear in Indexes to the Microfilmed Correspondence of Directors, Acting Directors and Selected Astronomers Among the Records of the Allegheny Observatory held by the Archives. In addition a large portion of the correspondence and letterpress books of Director Frank Schlesinger were microfilmed by the Center of History of Physics of the American Institute of Physics and the Archives of Industrial Society. The Schlesinger correspondence, ranging from 1905 through 1941, which was held by both the Archives of Industrial Society and the Center of History of Physics, Yale University Library was microfilmed as part of the project, "Sources for History of Modern Astrophysics."
Note: Additional notes and information are located at the series level including brief biographies of Directors.
A new series was added with the 2009 deposit to include some files on students affiliated with the Observatory.
New Material Added: Additional material was added in 2013 and includes additions to Series I (Correspondence of Directors and Acting Directors), Series IV (Correspondence of affiliated astronomers); Series VI (Administrative Files); Series VIII (Graphic Materials), Series XII (Organizations and Societies), Series XIII (Publications) and Series XVII (Photographs). An additional series, Series XVII (Student Records) was also created.
Access Restrictions
Series XVII. Student Records are restricted. Some papers in Series XII, Publications, have restrictions on the student records in the section called Reprints and Scholarly Papers. Access to this material is based on researcher signing a memo of confidentiality.
Acquisition Information
Original deposit by Nicholas Wagman, Director, Allegheny Observatory, on February 28, 1964. Second deposit of 9 boxes by Louis Coban on November 2, 2009.
Existence and Location of Copies
Series I, II, and IV have been microfilmed. A detailed inventory of those items microfilmed can be found in the unpublished "Indexes to the Microfilmed Correspondence of Directors, Acting Directors and Selected Astronomers Among the Records of the Allegheny Observatory" located at the Archives Service Center. In addition, a large portion of the correspondence of Director Frank Schlesinger and his letterpress books were microfilmed by the Curator in History of Physics of the American Institute of Physics. The correspondence, ranging from 1905 through 1941, held by both the Archives Service Center and the Yale University Library, was microfilmed as part of the project, "Sources for History of Modern Astrophysics" and is available in AIS.1981.06 microfilm (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9 and Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 1).
Digital reproductions of selected photographs can be found at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/allegheny-observatory-records.
Previous Citation
Allegheny Observatory Records, 1850-1967, UA.5.1, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Records of Allegheny Observatory, 1850-1967, ais 64.22, Archives of Industrial Society, Hillman Library, University of Pittsburgh.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following 16 series:
Series I. Correspondence of Directors / Acting Directors, 1850-1977
Series II. Letterpress Books of Directors / Acting Directors, 1862-1910
Series III. Directors / Acting Directors Miscellany, 1863-1978
Series IV. Correspondence of Affiliated Astronomers, 1886-1972
Series V. Affiliated Astronomers Miscellany
Series VI. Administrative Files, 1858-1977
Series VII. Observation, 1869-1930
Series VIII. Graphic Materials, 1878-1910
Series IX. Publicity, 1893-1902
Series X. Newsclippings (Miscellaneous), 1907-1947
Series XI. Scrapbooks, 1873-1917
Series XII. Organizations and Societies, 1899-1960
Series XIII. Publications, 1870-1939
Series XIV. Correspondence (Miscellaneous), 1881-1900
Series XV. History, 1912-1987
Series XVI. Photographs, 1886-1922
Series XVII. Student Records, 1960-1977
Correspondence; Notebooks; University of Pittsburgh; Astronomers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Biography; Clippings (Information artifacts); Photographs; Records (Documents); Astronomical Society of Pittsburgh; Jordan, Frank Craig -- Correspondence; Western University of Pennsylvania; Keeler, James Edward -- Correspondence; Langley, S. P. (Samuel Pierpont) -- Correspondence; Schlesinger, Frank -- Correspondence; University of Pittsburgh; Allegheny Observatory; Brashear, John A. (John Alfred); American Astronomical Society
- Correspondence of Directors/Acting Directors, 1850-1977; I.
  - Samuel Pierpoint Langley, 1850-1896, 1899; 1.
    Scope and Content Notes
    Samuel Pierpoint Langley was born in Roxbury, MA, on August 22, 1834 and was Director of the observatory from 1867-1887. After graduating from the Boston Latin School, he studied civil engineering and architecture. His first employment was as an assistant in the Observatory at Harvard University; soon afterwards he became an instructor at the United States Naval Academy at Annapolis. In 1867 Langley became the Director of the Allegheny Observatory which had been transferred from private hands to the Western University of Pennsylvania; at the same time he was elected to the chair of Astronomy and Physics at the University.
    Langley's main field of interest was the sun. He made detailed drawings of sunspots, invented the bolometer (an instrument to measure the amount of heat in different parts of the sun's spectrum), and obtained accurate time by using the telescope and positions of the stars. He also made accurate time available to Pittsburgh, City Hall, and to local railroads--even the U.S. Naval Observatory used his system (Allegheny System) to supply the correct time to the nation. During his term Mr. William Thaw contributed much money to the Observatory as did Andrew Carnegie who stated: "This was my first considerable gift to an institution of learning." Langley left to become first assistant secretary and then secretary to the Smithsonian Institute. He remained in that position until his death in 1906. Samuel Pierpont Langley died in Aiken, South Carolina, on February 26, 1906.
    - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ba-Be (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bi-Bu (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ca-Coo (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cop-De (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Du-El (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Er-Gilb (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Gill-Gr (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ha-Hilga (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hilge-Ho (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hu-Ki (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ki-Lel (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Les-Lone (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Longitude (Box 1, Folder 14-18)
    - Lou-McG (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Includes McConnel letter.
    - McI-Mai (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Mal-May (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Maz-Mid (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Mil-Mt (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Mu-Na (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Ne-Ob (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Oi-Pee (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Pem-Pen (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Ph-Pi (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Po-Rei (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Rep-Roq (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Roo-Sal (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - San-Sl (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Smil-Smit (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Sny-Stev (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Stew-Te (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Thaw (Box 2, Folder 36-42)
    - Th-Ts (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - U.S. Signal (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
    - U.S. Government Printing - U.S. Navy (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Up-Was (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Wat-We (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Wht (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Why-Y (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Addendum, 1871-1899 (Box 2, Folder 50A)
      - To: Barns, Carl B. (U.S. Geological Survey, Washington, D.C.), March 31, 1886-November 14, 1887
      - To: Pennsylvania Company (O.H. Booth, Superintendent, Mansfield, Ohio), March 18, 1873
      - From: Goff, M.B. (Chancellor, Western University of Pennsylvania), November 30, 1899
      - From: Meysan, Charles, esq. (Pittsburgh), December 2, 1871
  - Frank Washington Very, 1864-1895; 2.
    Frank Washington Very was Langley's assistant and was placed in charge of the observatory when Langley was appointed the Assistant Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution in 1887.
    - A-B (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - C (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - D-G (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - H-J (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - K-L (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - M-P (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Q-S (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - T-U (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - V-Z (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - James Edward Keeler, 1887-1898; 3.
    James Edward Keeler was Director from 1891-1898. Keeler used the 13-inch telescope to make spectroscopic studies and discovered that the rings of Saturn are not solid but composed of a multitude of small particles. In 1898, he left to become director of Lick Observatory.
    - Ac-Al (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Am (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - An-Astronomi (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Astronomy-At (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Au-Bar (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Bau-Bi (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Bl-Bos (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Bot-Bri (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Bro-Burc (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Brue-Cal (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Cam (Box 3, Folder 70-73)
    - Car-Chic (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Chid-Clap (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Clar-Cod (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Col-Cot (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Cre (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Cro-Da (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - De-Do (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Dr-Dz (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - E (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Fa-Fe (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Fi-Fr (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Gi-Gr (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Hale (Box 4, Folder 86-100)
    - Hale (Box 5, Folder 101-102)
    - Hall-Hapr (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Har-Hau (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Hay-Hof (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Hol (Box 5, Folder 106-108)
    - Hou-Hu (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Hy-Je (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Ji-Jo (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Ju (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Ka-Ki (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Ki-Led (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Lem-Li (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Lo (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Lu-Mat (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Man-Mil (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Min-Nel (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - New-No (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - O-Pat (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - Pay (Box 5, Folder 122-124)
    - Pay (Box 6, Folder 125-127)
    - Pe (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - Ph-Pie (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - Pih-Pot (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - Pr-Ramb (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - Rams-Reed (Box 6, Folder 132)
    - Rees-Roc (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - Rum-San (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - Sar-Scha (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - Schu-Si (Box 6, Folder 136)
    - Sh-So (Box 6, Folder 137)
    - Sp (Box 6, Folder 138)
    - Sta-Step (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - Steu-Sto (Box 6, Folder 140)
    - Str-Th (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - To-Ts (Box 6, Folder 142)
    - US (Box 6, Folder 143)
    - Un-Va (Box 6, Folder 144)
    - Vee (Box 6, Folder 145-147)
    - Vo-Wan (Box 6, Folder 148)
    - Wain (Box 6, Folder 149-150)
    - Warr-Way (Box 7, Folder 151)
    - Way, M. (Box 7, Folder 152)
    - We-Will (Box 7, Folder 153)
    - Wil-Wol (Box 7, Folder 154)
    - Woo-Ye (Box 7, Folder 155)
    - Yo-Z (Box 7, Folder 156)
    - University of Pittsburgh (Western University of Pennsylvania) (Box 7, Folder 157)
  - John Alfred Brashear, 1866-1903; 4.
    John Alfred Brashear was Director Pro Tem from 1898-1900. Brashear was originally a mill worker, but, encouraged by his friend S.P. Langley and financially supported by William Thaw, he became a renowned lens-maker, setting up the Brashear Company which constructed both the 30-inch Thaw Memorial Telescope and the James E. Keeler Memorial Telescope. In 1867 Brashear raised matching funds from Thaw and Carnegie and he and Keeler drew up plans for a new observatory and equipment. In 1898, Keeler declared "The Observatory's usefulness is at an end" due to antiquated equipment, the encroachment of homes, factories, and the smoky, hazy atmosphere which obscured vision. Brashear spoke eloquently for aid in constructing a new "Temple of the Skies," but both the Panic of 1893 and the War of 1898 hampered the raising of funds. Discouraged, Keeler left for Lick Observatory at the University of California.
    When Keeler died in 1906, his ashes were placed in the crypt of the memorial telescope built for him. Brashear persevered in his efforts to build a new observatory, eventually raising the $300,000 needed and securing a plot of land in Riverview Park. Appropriately, when the new observatory was dedicated in 1912, he was master of ceremonies (as he had been at the laying of the cornerstone in 1900). Upon their deaths, the ashes of both Brashear and his wife were also enclosed in the crypt (with Keeler's ashes) of the Keeler Memorial Telescope--the tablet bears the inscription "We have loved stars too fondly to be fearful of the night," words chosen by Brashear from "The Old Astronomer to His Pupil," a poem by Sarah William.
    - B-Ca (Box 7, Folder 158)
    - Co-Hal (Box 7, Folder 159)
    - Har (Box 7, Folder 160-166)
    - Has-Hu (Box 7, Folder 167)
    - L (Box 7, Folder 168)
    - Ma (Box 7, Folder 169)
    - Mc-Pg (Box 7, Folder 170)
    - Ph-S (Box 7, Folder 171)
    - T (Box 7, Folder 172-173)
    - U-V (Box 7, Folder 174)
    - W (Box 7, Folder 175)
    - Addendum - Unsigned Letter, Pittsburgh, August 27, 1887 (Box 7, Folder 175A)
  - F.L.O. Wadsworth, 1894-1905, 1907; 5.
    F.L.O. Wadsworth was Director from 1900-1905. It was during Wadsworth's directorship on October 20, 1900 that the cornerstone of the new building was laid. Modifying and adding to the plans he was mostly concerned with the supervision of the construction of the new buildings and instruments. He also exerted his influence, along with Brashear and the Observatory Committee, in raising the needed funds. The Observatory was completed in 1905, but the work of equipping it delayed dedication until 1912.
    - Ab-Ae (Box 8, Folder 176)
    - Ab-Alb (Box 8, Folder 177)
    - Ale-Alle (Box 8, Folder 178)
    - Alli-American (Box 8, Folder 179)
    - American B-American J (Box 8, Folder 180)
    - American L-American W (Box 8, Folder 181)
    - Ames (Box 8, Folder 182)
    - Amh-Ar (Box 8, Folder 183)
    - Astronomic (Box 8, Folder 184)
    - Astronomics-Ay (Box 8, Folder 185)
    - Bac-Baker (Box 8, Folder 186)
    - Baker (Box 8, Folder 187-189)
    - Bakh (Box 8, Folder 190)
    - Bal-Barr (Box 8, Folder 191)
    - Barr-Bec (Box 8, Folder 192)
    - Bed-Ber (Box 8, Folder 193)
    - Bi (Box 8, Folder 194)
    - Bl-Bol (Box 8, Folder 195)
    - Bon (Box 8, Folder 196)
    - Bor-Bow (Box 8, Folder 197)
    - Bra (Box 8, Folder 198-199)
    - Bre-Brown (Box 8, Folder 200)
    - Bou-Bur (Box 9, Folder 201)
    - Burn-By (Box 9, Folder 202)
    - Cad-Came (Box 9, Folder 203)
    - Camph (Box 9, Folder 204)
    - Can-Carnegie (Box 9, Folder 205)
    - Caregies (Box 9, Folder 206)
    - Cas-Cau (Box 9, Folder 207)
    - Cent (Box 9, Folder 208)
    - Chab-Chan (Box 9, Folder 209)
    - Chan-Chic (Box 9, Folder 210)
    - Chil (Box 9, Folder 211)
    - Chr-Clark, G. (Box 9, Folder 212)
    - Clark, U. (Box 9, Folder 213)
    - Cle (Box 9, Folder 214)
    - Cob-Col (Box 9, Folder 215)
    - Com-Cop (Box 9, Folder 216)
    - Cn-Cow (Box 9, Folder 217)
    - Cr (Box 9, Folder 218)
    - Cr-Dam (Box 9, Folder 219)
    - Dave-Davi, L.C. (Box 9, Folder 220)
    - Davi, H. (Box 9, Folder 221)
    - Davi W.-Der (Box 9, Folder 222)
    - Det-Di (Box 9, Folder 223)
    - Do (Box 9, Folder 224)
    - Dr (Box 9, Folder 225)
    - Eb-Ec (Box 10, Folder 226)
    - Ed-Elk (Box 10, Folder 227)
    - Ell-En (Box 10, Folder 228)
    - Eq-Ev (Box 10, Folder 229)
    - Fa (Box 10, Folder 230)
    - Fe-For (Box 10, Folder 231)
    - Fos-Fow (Box 10, Folder 232)
    - Fra-Fri (Box 10, Folder 233)
    - Fro-fu (Box 10, Folder 234)
    - Ga-Gi (Box 10, Folder 235)
    - Gi-Go (Box 10, Folder 236)
    - Gr-Hag (Box 10, Folder 237)
    - Hale (Box 10, Folder 238-244)
    - Hall-Ham (Box 10, Folder 245)
    - Har (Box 10, Folder 246)
    - Has (Box 10, Folder 247)
    - Harv (Box 10, Folder 248-249)
    - Haw-Hen (Box 10, Folder 250)
    - Her (Box 11, Folder 251)
    - Hev-Hoo (Box 11, Folder 252)
    - Hos-Howa (Box 11, Folder 253)
    - Howe-Hul (Box 11, Folder 254)
    - Hum-Hut (Box 11, Folder 255)
    - Hus-Ins (Box 11, Folder 256)
    - Int-Ir (Box 11, Folder 257)
    - Ja-Joh (Box 11, Folder 258)
    - Jon (Box 11, Folder 259)
    - Ju-Kat (Box 11, Folder 260)
    - Kay-Ke (Box 11, Folder 261)
    - Kev-Ki (Box 11, Folder 262)
    - Kin (Box 11, Folder 263)
    - Kk-Ko (Box 11, Folder 264)
    - Kra (Box 11, Folder 265)
    - Kre-Lawa (Box 11, Folder 266)
    - Lea-Leo (Box 11, Folder 267)
    - Les-Li (Box 11, Folder 268)
    - Loc-Loo (Box 11, Folder 269)
    - Lord (Box 11, Folder 270-272)
    - Lore-McA (Box 11, Folder 273)
    - MacB-McP (Box 11, Folder 274)
    - Mag-Marq (Box 11, Folder 275)
    - Mari-Mel (Box 12, Folder 276)
    - Men-Merria (Box 12, Folder 277)
    - Merril (Box 12, Folder 278)
    - Merrit-Met (Box 12, Folder 279)
    - Mic-Mil (Box 12, Folder 280)
    - Min-Mou (Box 12, Folder 281)
    - Mur-Mut (Box 12, Folder 282)
    - My-Nam (Box 12, Folder 283)
    - Nat-Nau (Box 12, Folder 284)
    - New (Box 12, Folder 285)
    - Nich-Nis (Box 12, Folder 286)
    - Nors-North (Box 12, Folder 287)
    - North W-Observatoire C (Box 12, Folder 288)
    - Observatoire DeB-Observatoire Der (Box 12, Folder 289)
    - Observatoire DeZ-Observatoire M (Box 12, Folder 290)
    - Observatoire M-Observatoire N (Box 12, Folder 291)
    - Observatoire N-Observatoy C (Box 12, Folder 292)
    - Observatory G-Observatory T (Box 12, Folder 293)
    - Oe-Ol (Box 12, Folder 294)
    - On-Os (Box 12, Folder 295)
    - Pag-Pat (Box 12, Folder 296)
    - Pau-Pen (Box 12, Folder 297)
    - Per-Pet (Box 12, Folder 298)
    - Ph-Pic (Box 12, Folder 299)
    - Pie-Pit (Box 12, Folder 300)
    - Pl-Pop (Box 13, Folder 301)
    - Por-Poy (Box 13, Folder 302)
    - Pra (Box 13, Folder 303)
    - Pre-Ram (Box 13, Folder 304)
    - Ras-Rat (Box 13, Folder 305)
    - Ray-Roose, A. (Box 13, Folder 306)
    - Reese, H.-Reg (Box 13, Folder 307)
    - Rep-Rie (Box 13, Folder 308)
    - Rob-Roo (Box 13, Folder 309)
    - R.T.-R.O. (Box 13, Folder 310)
    - Roy (Box 13, Folder 311)
    - Ru-Sca (Box 13, Folder 312)
    - Sch-Scho (Box 13, Folder 313)
    - Schu-Se (Box 13, Folder 314)
    - Sec-See (Box 13, Folder 315)
    - Sh-Smith (Box 13, Folder 316)
    - Smiths (Box 13, Folder 317)
    - Sn (Box 13, Folder 318-321)
    - Soc-Sol (Box 13, Folder 322)
    - Som-Stah (Box 13, Folder 323)
    - Standard R. (Box 13, Folder 324)
    - Standard U-Steb (Box 13, Folder 325)
    - Stec (Box 14, Folder 326-328)
    - Ster-Sterr (Box 14, Folder 329)
    - Sted-Skw (Box 14, Folder 330)
    - Sti-Strab (Box 14, Folder 331)
    - Strat (Box 14, Folder 332-333)
    - Straw-Sy (Box 14, Folder 334)
    - Ta-Th (Box 14, Folder 335)
    - Ti-Tu (Box 14, Folder 336)
    - Uf-U.S.B. (Box 14, Folder 337)
    - U.S. C-U.S. Coa (Box 14, Folder 338)
    - U.S. Col-U.S. Ge (Box 14, Folder 339)
    - U.S. Gl-U.S.N. (Box 14, Folder 340)
    - U.S.O.-Univ (Box 14, Folder 341)
    - Up-Va (Box 14, Folder 342)
    - Ve-Wal (Box 14, Folder 343)
    - War-Wat (Box 14, Folder 344)
    - Web-Wesh (Box 14, Folder 345)
    - Westi-Whifn (Box 14, Folder 346)
    - Whill-Wilson L. (Box 14, Folder 347)
    - Wilson M.-Wood, E.M. (Box 14, Folder 348)
    - Wood, R.W.-Wu (Box 14, Folder 349)
    - Ya-Z (misc.) (Box 14, Folder 350)
    - Addendum, 1894-1904
      - A-D (Box 14, Folder 350A)
      - E-K (Box 14, Folder 350B)
      - L-W (Box 14, Folder 350C)
  - Frank Schlesinger, 1899-1920, 1907; 6.